Ready? If you dove into the ocean off the coast
of Sicily, you'd suddenly be surrounded by over
900 of these mysterious balls like ...these. They
hook these up on a string, wind them up into
an even bigger ball, and then drop them into the
ocean where they unroll to nearly twice the height
of the Empire State Building ... again and again and
again, creating this massive forest of floating
spheres. And on the surface, hidden inside an
abandoned winery, a computer watches them andwaits...
And in 2023, they saw something. Something
way smaller than an electron tore through this
forest at nearly the speed of light setting
off a signal nearly 30 times more powerful
than anything we'd ever seen like it before. Which
means that something huge must have happened way
out there in space. So all of these telescopes
all around the world swing in that direction to
see what it might be and they find ....nothing. Now
scientists are searching for answers. And this
crazy experiment is getting bigger. But it's
not alone. Down at the bottom of the world,
buried deep in Antarctic ice, are over 5,000 more
of these mysterious balls. This is Ice Cube and
this is KM3NET. And together they're part of a
massive global effort to give us a brand new way
to find and look inside the biggest, most extreme
cosmic events in our universe. But to do it,
they need to catch the most elusive particle in
all of physics. And we're going to show you how.
This episode was made possible by AT&T, the
official connectivity partner of HUGE*If True.
Imagine that you and I get into a spaceship and
we fly to the next closest star. It's nearly 40
trillion km away, a distance that could fit nearly
29 million of our sun, which means that we're
flying for 75,000 years. And that's just about the
average distance for all the stars in our galaxy.
There's just a lot of space in space. If instead
we shrink down to the size of one of the tiniest
fundamental particles in physics, the space
between the stars would be like the distance
between the nucleus of atoms to us now. That
means that we could zoom right through the atoms
of solid rock as easily as flying between the
stars in space. That is what it's like to be a
neutrino. It's another fundamental particle like
electrons, but way smaller. If you scaled this
particle up even just a millimeter in size, a
human being would be like the size of an entire
galaxy. It's really hard to understand just how
close to nothing these particles actually are.
Their nickname is the 'ghost particle' because
they pass through basically everything. Stars,
planets, walls, even ... you. Every single second
100 trillion neutrinos pass through your body.
Hold up your thumb right now. That's what's
happening right there. But this fly through
walls superpower is what makes neutrinos so awesome
as a way to study what's really happening out
there in our universe. Because everything else
that we've used so far has a big problem. When
we want to understand what's happening way
out there, we can only use what reaches us.
And up until this point, there have been three
options. Most of the time, we use option one,
light. Not just visible light, but everything made
up of photons, radio waves, infrared, gamma rays,
but other things reach us too. Like option two,
these really high energy charged particles called
cosmic rays. Scientists study these to learn about
the chemistry of deep space. And option three,
ripples in spacetime called gravitational waves.
But while these methods have taught us so much,
the big problem is this one gets blocked,
reflected, and warped. This one gets tossed
around by magnetic fields in space. And this one
can only tell us when something massive happens,
not what it did or what it's made of. Meaning,
there are things that we might never discover
because the evidence took a wrong turn on the
way to Earth. That is why neutrinos are special.
They're a new fourth option to study what's
out there. Their size means they're incredibly
unlikely to get blocked by anything in their
path. And they have no charge, so they don't
get warped by electric or magnetic fields, which
means that they travel straight to us at almost
the speed of light. If you can catch neutrinos,
you can trace back exactly where they came from
and even see inside whatever made them. A good
analogy would be a doctor giving you an exam.
Visible light can show them some things, but if
they wanted to see your bones, "you can use X-rays,
right? And the reason X-rays are useful is
because they could interact with muscle and
tissue and skin less than ordinary kinds of light
do." So catching neutrinos is like developing X-ray
vision for our universe. So, for example, around
every 10 seconds, somewhere in the universe, a
star collapses in a supernova, releasing a massive
burst of energy, blasting particles out into the
universe at up to 40,000 km/s. We think these
explosions are the primary sources of elements
like silicon and oxygen and iron. And those
elements make up the universe and planets and
us. The iron in your blood can be traced back to
a supernova, which is why these events are called
cosmic engines. Scientists think that cosmic
rays come from here, but they can't be positive
cuz we can't trace them. And light can show us
the aftermath of a supernova. But light takes
forever to get out past all this dense matter at
the center. So... "if you want to know what's going
on inside the core of a supernova, neutrinos
are your messenger." But wait, if the whole
point is that neutrinos are so special to study
because they can go through anything, how do you...
...catch one. "The problem is that neutrinos interact
so weakly that if it's great for them to pass
through everything, well, they can also pass
through our own detectors." How do you study
something that never interacts with you at all?
You build a very, very big and very crazy machine.
So right now I'm at the lab in Caserta, Italy,
where they're putting together the detectors
that make up this giant underwater experiment.
When this experiment is finished, it'll take up
a cubic kilometer in the Mediterranean
Sea. That's where its name comes from,
cubic km neutrino telescope. The entire project is
technically two telescopes, and we're focusing on
this bigger one over here. Each of these spheres
is called a DOM. And inside each DOM is a huge
amount of delicate tech that has to survive in
the deep sea. And they piece each one together
here by hand, one hemisphere at a time. You start
with one glass half and this aluminum piece right
here that you glue in place with this special
gel. "Pay attention to the air bubbles." Okay.
It's done. It's done. "Well done. And
sign it, by the way." "Yeah, go on"
Thank you! "You're welcome" That's the HUGE* DOM.
Now, the HUGE* DOM needs a brain, a mini computer
that tells it what to do, and 31 of these.
These are its eyes, the photo multipliers,
which you fit very carefully into this 3D
printed frame. He's checking my work. "Yeah,
you did a good job, all things considered, for the
first time." The most important thing here is that
these photo multipliers are incredibly sensitive
to light. Each one is sensitive enough to detect a
single photon. That's insane. That's like standing
in the middle of a hurricane and hearing a single
drop on a single leaf. But wait, this is a neutrino
telescope. Why are we trying to detect light? "So,
we actually cannot see neutrino." Wait...what?
"We don't have the technology to do that, even
though there are hundreds of them in every
cubic centimeter of space today." So instead,
they found a very clever way to detect
what happens in the unlikely times when
a neutrino actually does just happen to crash into
something. From the little neutrinos's perspective,
what happens is it's born in some massive
cosmic event like a supernova or a super
massive black hole with jets of plasma, but it
escapes... and for the next billion years it goes
in a straight line. "Not that they're sentient or
something, but if they were, it would be a dull
billion years." And then one day... "and then they
come up to this little pale blue dot Earth and
uh they don't really care that it's there. You
know, they've traveled through a lot of stuff..." But
not this time. This neutrino just happens to fly
right through the Earth... and then just by chance,
it accidentally runs head first into some poor
proton. And that proton just happens to be
inside a water molecule right here off Sicily or
inside the ice right here in Antarctica, which I
know sounds incredibly unlikely, but remember a
100 trillion of them through your body every
single second. So, statistically, some of them
will bump into something. And when that happens...
Wait...slow that down...
The neutrino hits the proton, changing it into a
different, heavier particle, which flies through
the water faster than light. This is part of
the reason why KM3NET sits 3,500m under water.
And nothing can go faster than the speed of light
in vacuum. But light slows down a lot in water. So
there are actually particles that can go faster
than the speed of light in water. And when they
do, they create waves of light making this cone
shape behind them. Is it sort of like a sonic
boom? Something is moving faster than sound, and
so there's like a wave around it in a cone? "It is
exactly like a sonic boom." In this case, instead
of going faster than the speed of sound and making
a boom, they go faster than the speed of light
in water and make a flash of blue light. THAT is
what these sensors can see. If you were down
there in the water with your eyes wide open,
this is visible light, but most of the flash is so
faint and so fast that your eyes probably couldn't
see it. But that's what these sensors were built
for. "That light is picked up by hundreds or maybe
thousands of these optical sensors." Every detector
has to be exactly the same. Every photo multiplier
has to be in perfect sync. When this experiment
is fully built, there are going to be over 4,000
of these at the bottom of the Mediterranean Sea.
It takes about a month to build and test 18 DOMs,
which is just one single string. And then you
spool that string up into what they call LOMs,
which are these giant balls. This is what they're
going to drop into the ocean. On the top is a buoy
to hold them up. And on the bottom is an anchor
with a base module. And then from the bottom of
the base module, there are these big orange cables
that connect all the way to the shore to that
abandoned winery turned science lab where "they're
gathered together a computer and uh you know,
next thing you know, some scientists are looking
at this and and saying, 'Hey, I think we just saw
a neutrino.'" But it's really hard to make sure that
this computer sees just this special blue light.
and not anything else. Because while there's less
light down there, it's not zero. They have to
ignore lots and lots of photons created by all
kinds of things like bioluminescent microorganisms
and all kinds of other particles raining down on
this machine from above. In order to weed those
out, these machines mostly look at particles small
enough to pass through the Earth. So, when you're
thinking about this experiment, don't think about
it like hundreds of detectors on strings sticking
up out of the ocean and looking up above it. Think
about it instead as the back of a giant telescope
where the lens is the entire Earth. KM3NET won't
be completely done for a few more years. It's
operational right now, but it's not at its full
capacity. But down in Antarctica is its sister,
Ice Cube. That one's been operational for over
a decade now. Instead of water, they use ice,
which on its own is a massive engineering feat.
And because each experiment is mostly focusing on
neutrinos coming through the Earth...this is what
KM3NET sees, and this is what Ice Cube sees. They
complete each other. Just take a second to think
about how incredible this is. Humans are amazing.
But what's amazing isn't just the infrastructure.
It's also what they found with it. In 2017,
a high energy neutrino tore through Antarctic
ice, setting off ice cube and telling scientists
around the world to swing their telescopes in that
direction. And they found a flaring active galaxy,
a blazar over 4 billion lightyears away. That
we'd seen before with visible light and gamma
rays, but it wasn't until we saw the neutrino
that we could confirm this is a cosmic engine,
the source of heavy metals that make up
everything, including us, and a source of
cosmic rays. This moment marked the beginning
of a whole new era in astronomy. One where we
could use all four options, photons, cosmic rays,
gravitational waves, AND neutrinos to see things
in an entirely new way. And it took such a huge
effort, just look at this. There are nearly a
thousand scientists on this paper. This was a huge
deal and they just kept going. In 2022, Ice Cube
identified an active galaxy nearly 50 million
light years away. You can actually see it from the
ground with a normal telescope. But its core was
completely hidden by gas and dust. Light couldn't
escape, so we couldn't see inside. But neutrinos
could and did. So, we got the first ever look
inside a cosmic engine that light could never show
us. "This is one of the most exciting things to
happen in in modern astronomy. Um, it's really a
watershed moment, not just for neutrino astronomy,
but for astrophysics in general." And in 2023, when
that most powerful signal ever came through KM3NET,
the one that we still don't know where it came
from, it showed us that there is so so much more
to discover with neutrinos. "It just opens
a whole new kind of eye unto the universe.
This is a truly like, you know, one of a kind of
event in human experience so far." We've created a
new way to see inside our universe. And what
I love most about this story isn't just what
we could discover with neutrinos. It's also
what the effort says about us as humans. "I
was a factory worker before." You're building this
incredible thing that is going to move forward our
understanding of the universe. "Yeah, I'm pretty
proud of that." That's awesome. Because what are
the machines that we build if not extensions
of ourselves to be our brain and our eyes and
our ears and take us places we could never go and
show us things we could never see. HUGE* if true.
If you like this and you want more optimistic
science and tech stories in your life,
subscribe to support our show. And remember,
this episode was made possible by AT&T, the
official connectivity partner of HUGE* If True.